Register of the Sabin Manuila Papers, 1893-1976
Hoover Institution Archives
Sabin Manuila Papers,
1893-1976
76102
Manuila, Sabin, 1894-1964
21 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (9.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, speeches and writings, clippings, printed matter, and other material, relating to political events in Romania, and Romanian anti-communist emigre movements.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Paris Peace Conference (1946); Anti-communist movements--United States.; Civil rights--Europe, Eastern.; Civil rights--Romania.; Communism.; Forced labor--Romania.; Romanians in foreign countries.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Romania.; Europe, Eastern.; Romania.; Romania--History--1944-1989.; Romania--Politics and government.; Romania--Social conditions.; United States.; Maniu, Iuliu, 1873-1953.
Biographical Note
Sabin Manuila was born in Transilvania in 1894.
He was the director of the first Central Institute of Statistics of Romania, and member of the Romanian Academy. He was also a member of the International Institute of Sociology, member of various committees of the League of Nations, member of the International Institute of Statistics, and vice-president of the Royal Society of Heredity. A former Rockefeller Foundation fellow, he received financial support from this foundation for the organization of the first demographic census of Romania. In 1948 he established himself in New York and became politically involved. His work with the "Iuliu Maniu" Foundation and the Romanian National Committee greatly supported Romanian political refugees.
He worked for the Institute for Food Research of Stanford University, where he contributed to the study The Agricultural Economy of the Danubian Countries: 1935-1945. Later, he became the Counselor for the US Bureau of Census in Washington.
His studies, "The Population of Romania" (1937) and "The Structure of Evolution of the Rural Population" are among the most famous Romanian demographic studies. Also, his paper "Regional Development of the Jewish Population in Romania" is considered among the most reliable statistical data regarding the Jewish population of Romania.
Scope and Content
This collection consists mainly of Sabin Manuila's correspondence with various Romanian émigré associations and former politicians. Of special interest are the materials related to Iuliu Maniu, found in the subject file, which include his correspondence with important statesmen like I. Bratianu, I. Antonescu, and his original articles, depositions, discourses, memoranda, declarations, writings, and speeches.
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1948-1964. (Box No. 1.)
  Obituaries, resume, and scrapbook of biographical information, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1946-1971. (Box No. 1.-4.)
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1948-1964. (Box No. 5.-7.)
  Articles, papers, studies, speeches, and miscellaneous writings, arranged chronologically by title
- SUBJECT FILE, 1893-1976. (Box No. 7.-22.)
  Includes miscellaneous material arranged alphabetically by subject, and related mainly to Romanian émigré associations, to former democratic Romanian parties, and to Iuliu Maniu
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1938-1959. (Box No. 23.)
  20 prints depicting mainly activities of the Assembly of Captive European Nations,and Romanian former politicians
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1948-1964
  - Obituaries, 1964 (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Resume, n.d. (Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook of biographical information. Includes prints depicting Manuila, correspondence, official papers, and biographical notes, 1948-1964 (Folder 3)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1646-1971.
  See also SUBJECT FILE/ International Peasant Union; International Institute of Statistics; Maniu, Iuliu; National Committee for a Free Europe; Romanian National Committee; Romanian University Institute Carol I
  - General, 1947-1963. Consists mainly of personal letters with friends (Box 1.)
    - Undated (Folder 4)
    - 1947 (Folder 5)
    - 1948 (Folder 6-7)
    - 1949 (Folder 8)
    - 1950 (Folder 9)
    - 1951 (Box 2., Folder 1-2)
    - 1952 (Folder 3)
    - 1953 (Folder 4)
    - 1954-1955 (Folder 5)
    - 1956 (Folder 6)
    - 1957-1958 (Folder 7)
    - 1959-1960 (Folder 8)
    - 1961-1963 (Folder 9)
  - Unidentified, 1948-1959 (Folder 10-11)
  - Bianu, Cornel, 1948-1958 (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - Brailoiu, Constantin, 1951 (Folder 2)
  - Bratianu, Vintila, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - Carp, Mircea, 1954 (Folder 4)
  - Cieslicki, Frans, 1950 (Folder 5)
  - Cretianu, Alexandru, 1949-1953 (Folder 6)
  - Dunham, Donald, 1949-1952 (Folder 7)
  - Eliade, Mircea, 1948 (Folder 8)
  - Emerson, Haven, 1948-1949 (Folder 9)
  - Free International Academy of Sciences and Letters, 1963-1964 (Folder 10)
  - Gafencu, Grigore, 1948 (Folder 11)
  - Georgescu-Roegen, 1950-1952 (Folder 12)
  - Ghilezeanu, Emil, 1949 (Folder 13)
  - Gusti, 1948-1952 (Folder 14)
  - Hatzegan, Vasile, 1949-1961 (Folder 15)
  - Ionescu, Ghita, 1951 (Folder 16)
  - Ionnitiu, Mircea, 1951-1967 (Folder 17)
  - Knowland, William, 1955 (Folder 18)
  - Lukacs, A., 1949 (Folder 19)
  - McCarthy, Joseph R., 1953 (Folder 20)
  - Melbourne, Roy, 1948-1951 (Folder 21)
  - Michael I, King of Romania, 1948 (Folder 22)
  - Morris, Evan, 1951-1953 (Folder 23)
  - Neumann-Grigg, Emanuel, 1949 (Folder 24)
  - Pauker, Guy, 1949-1950 (Folder 25)
  - Petre-Lazar, Constantin, 1957 (Folder 26)
  - Pop, Sever, 1953 (Folder 27)
  - Popovici, Andrei, 1948-1964 (Folder 28-29)
  - Prundeanu, Iulian, 1951 (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - Radescu, Nicolae, 1948 (Folder 2)
  - Rice, Stuart, 1948-1950 (Folder 3)
  - Rugina, Anghel, 1950-1958 (Folder 4)
  - Safran, David, 1960-1971 (Folder 5)
  - Serdici, Georges, 1952 (Folder 6)
  - Shirlaw, Gerald, 1948-1949 (Folder 7)
  - Sokolsky, George, 1950 (Folder 8)
  - Veniamin, Virgil, 1948-1958 (Folder 9)
  - Visoianu, Constantin, 1952 (Folder 10)
  - Watson, Seton, 1946 (Folder 11-12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1948-1955 (Folder 13-15)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1948-1964.
  See also SUBJECT FILE/ Jews, Romanians; National Committee for a Free Europe; Romania: Politics and Government
  - "Administrative Units," n.d. Holograph and typescript (Box 5., Folder 1)
  - "Basic Study of Ethnic Minority Groups in the World," n.d. Typescript (Folder 2)
  - "Dela Vlahistan la Pakeristan," n.d. Holograph (Folder 3)
  - "Ethnic Composition in the Historical Provinces of Romania in the 1930, 1941, and 1948 Census," n.d. Holograph and typescript (Folder 4)
  - "Few Remarks on Soviet Manpower and Colonialism," n.d. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - "Households," n.d. Notes, holograph, and typescript (Folder 6)
  - "Is the Marshall Plan the Future Answer for the Liberated Iron Curtain Countries?" n.d. Typescript (Folder 7)
  - "Un moment culminant in progresul sovietismului: Discutie asupra 'Situatiei din Ungaria' dela Consiliu de Securitate al ONU-ului," n.d. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - "Moralitatea sovietica si moralitatea americana," n.d. Holograph and typescript (Folder 9)
  - "Non-Romanians Speaking the Romanian Language," n.d. Notes, holograph, and typescript (Folder 10)
  - "Sugestiuni pentru combaterea sustinuta a infiltratiei comuniste in lumea libera," n.d. Holograph and typescript (Folder 11)
  - "Francmasoneria si patriotismul," 1948. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - "Profesorul Grigore Popa," 1948. Typescript (Folder 13)
  - Radio broadcast transcript, Christmas, 1949. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - "Are the Russians Planning to Make War on US?" 1950. Typescript (Folder 15)
  - Outline of the Agricultural Project for the Danubian Inquiry, 1950. Holograph and typescript (Folder 16)
  - "The 'Soviet Typ' Replay Due to Be Expected to the U.S. 'Note' of 18th of April, 1950," 1950. Holograph (Folder 17)
  - Commentary to George F. Kennan's article in the New York Times Magazine, 1951 February 28, "Let Peace Not Die of Neglect," 1951. Typescript (Folder 18)
  - "Experiences Behind the Iron Curtain," speech, Ithaca, 1951. Typescript (Folder 19)
  - "Galaxy of World Events and their Future Consequences," 1951. Typescript (Folder 20)
  - Newspaper articles, 1951-1956. Holograph and typescript (Folder 21)
  - Speech given on the occasion of the International Peasant Union Conference, 1952. Typescript (Folder 22)
  - Paper on the representatives of the peoples behind the Iron Curtain, 1953. Typescript (Folder 23)
  - "Primacy of Politics in Shaping Humanity's Future," paper, International Peasant Union Conference, 1953. Typescript (Folder 24)
  - "On Past Experiences and Future Prospects of Countries (Folder 25)
  - Aiming for Adequate Statistical Organization," paper presented to the XIVth Seminar on Censuses and Statistics, Washington, 1954. Typescript
  - "Population Studies: Romania," 1954 (Box 6.)
    - "Census in Romania," 1948. Miscellaneous notes (Folder 1)
    - "Ethnic Composition of the Population," n.d. (Folder 2)
    - Notes, holograph, and typescript
    - "Proiectiuni pe harta militara," 1954. Notes and holograph (Folder 3)
  - "Public Opinion in Romania," 1954. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - "Internal Migration," 1955(?). Holograph (Folder 5)
  - "Citizenship," 1955. Holograph and typescript (Folder 6)
  - "Religion," 1955. Holograph and typescript (Folder 7)
  - "Schooling," 1955. Holograph (Folder 8)
  - "Some Fallacies in the Ideas of Co-Existence," 1955. Typescript (Folder 9)
  - "Alegeri libere: Zece ani de la alegerile parlamentare din noembrie 1946," 1956. Typescript (Folder 10)
  - Memorandum on the creation of the International Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1956. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - "Memoriul Comitetului National Roman cu privire la discriminarea in educatie in Bulgaria," 1956. (Folder 12)
  - Holograph and typescript
  - "Situatia din Ungaria in discutia Natiunilor Unite," 1956. Typescript (Folder 13)
  - "Sugestiuni pentru extinderea activitatii ANEC," 1956. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - "Constantin Brancusi si Vasile Cucui," 1957. Typescript (Box 7., Folder 1)
  - "Raporturile de colaborare cu fortele eliberatoare," 1957. Holograph (Folder 2)
  - Memorandum on the creation of a Technical Consultation Center at the Headquarters of the Assembly of Captive European Nations, 1958. Typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Magazine," 1959. Typescript (written by Manuila?) (Folder 4)
  - "The Absence of Freedom of Information in the Captive Countries: Its Meaning and Consequences," address, Assembly of Captive European Nations, 1961. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - "Effects of War upon Population," paper, XXth Congress of the International Institute of Sociology, Cordoba, Argentina, 1963. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - "Social Consequences of Displacements of Populations," Report written by Manuila for the Committee for the Study of Sociological Consequences of Displacements of Populations, Institute of Sociology, Congress, Cordoba, Argentina, 1963. Typescript (Folder 7)
  - "Notes About the Book Ploiesti by J. Dugan and C. Stuart," 1964. Hollograph (Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1945-1961 (Folder 9-11)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1893-1976
  - Assembly of Captive European Nations (A.C.E.N.), 1949-1971 (Box 7., Folder 12-15)
  - Boila, Romulus, 1954-1969 (Box 8., Folder 1)
  - Davila, C., 1952 (Folder 2)
  - Dragu, Ion, 1949-1952 (Folder 3)
  - Hannon, Stuart, 1955-1961 (Folder 4)
  - Hohenzollern, House of, 1916-1939 (Folder 5)
  - International Peasant Union, 1933-1954. Includes I.P.U. bulletins, reports, declarations agendas, and Manuila's correspondence with I.P.U. (Folder 6-11)
  - Institute of World Affairs, 1952-1955. Includes Manuila's correspondence with the Institute (Folder 12-14)
  - International Red Cross. "Memorandum to the International Red Cross Conference in Toronto, Canada, July 23rd 1952, on Behalf of the Former Red Cross Societies of Albania, Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Poland, Romania, and by the Red Cross Societies of Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania," 1952 (Folder 15)
  - Jews, Romanian, 1934-1963. Includes Manuila's correspondence with the International Institute of Statistics, C. Visoianu, and W. Filderman, and Manuila's studies "Regional Development of the Jewish Population in Romania" (1957) and "Populatia Evreiasca din Romania" (1958) (Box 9., Folder 1-3)
  - Malaxa, Nicolae, 1948-1956. Includes confidential and secret report on Malaxa case, 1948 (Folder 4)
  - Maniu, Iuliu, 1893-1969. Includes biographical notes, obituaries, letters between Romanian émigré associations concerning Maniu's imprisonment and death, clippings concerning Maniu's activity and life, a special edition of America magazine dedicated to Maniu's life and political activities (1962), original articles, depositions, discourses, memoranda, declarations, writings, and speeches by Maniu; correspondence of Maniu with Antonescu, Cornel Bianu, Gh. Tatarescu, V. Pop, Filderman, M. Camciciv, Michael, King of Romania, S. Manuila, A. Cretzianu, C. Davila, M. Cristea, B. Ionascu. Includes also Maniu's correspondence with S. Manuila (Folder 5-13)
  - Maniu, Iuliu (Box 10., Folder 1-6)
  - Maniu, Iuliu (Box 11., Folder 1-8)
  - Manuila, Venturia, 1943-1976. Includes transcripts of her talks for Radio Free Europe in her capacity of member of the National Council of Romanian Women in Exile, her correspondence (including with C. Sporea, Al. Cretzianu), and her papers concerning international committees for the assistance of Romanian refugees (Box 12., Folder 1-8)
  - Michael I, King of Romania, 1947-1964. Clippings (Box 13., Folder 1-2)
  - National Peasant Party, 1947-1952. Includes clippings and notes concerning the National Peasant Party in exile (Folder 3-6)
  - National Peasant Party, 1947-1952 (Contd.). Issues of the National Peasant Party's newspaper Dreptatea, 1945-1946 (Box 14., Folder 1-2)
  - National Committee for a Free Europe, 1952-1954. Includes Manuila's correspondence with Mid-European Studies Center, National Committee for a Free Europe, Cronica Romaneasca, East European Inquiry (Folder 3-6)
  - National Committee for a Free Europe, 1952-1954 (Contd.). Documents concerning Manuila's cooperation with the National Committee for a Free Europe; Manuila's articles related to the National Committee for a Free Europe; "Declaration of Liberation" issued by the National Committee for a Free Europe; exchange of letters and memoranda between the State Department, Romanian politicians in exile, and the National Committee for a Free Europe; agricultural reports; Danubian Inquiry outlines (Box 15., Folder 1-9)
  - Neferi, Dumitru, 1953-1957 (Box 16., Folder 1)
  - Nicolescu-Buzesti, Grigore, 1949 (Folder 2)
  - Pauker, Ana, 1949-1964 (Folder 3)
  - Popovici, Andrei, 1948-1955 (Folder 4)
  - Romania
    - History
      - 1914-1944. Consists of one booklet, Romania and the Revision of Treaties containing the speeches of I. Maniu and C. I. C. Bratianu, 1934 (Folder 5)
      - 1944-1989. Includes clippings and documents related to the Romanian Armistice in 1944. Includes also a memorandum and commentaries on the Romanian Peace of 1946 (Folder 6-16)
    - Law
      - Administrative law, 1950 (Folder 17)
      - Constitution, 1938 (Folder 18)
    - Politics and Government (Box 17.)
      - 1914-1944. Scrapbook and clippings (Folder 1-3)
  - Romania (Box 18.)
    - Politics and Government
      - 1944-1989. Clippings, reports, notes. Includes reports of the US House of Representatives and Assembly of Captive European Nations on the forceful takeover of power by communists in Romania. Also includes a list of some political leaders, and of high government officials incarcerated in Romanian communist prisons from 1946 on (compiled by Manuila?) (Folder 1-8)
      - 1944-1989 (Contd.) (Box 19., Folder 1-3)
  - Romanian National Committee, 1948-1975. Includes papers related to discussions concerning political cooperation among representatives of former Romanian democratic parties and the creation of the Council of Political Parties and of the Romanian National Committee. Comprises also reports of the Committee concerning the activities of the Welfare Office, financial papers related to the Committee loan funds, clippings and notices regarding forced labor and deportations in Romania, and correspondence between the Committee and Romanian relief organizations. Includes also Manuila's correspondence related to the Committee's work (with N. Radescu, M. Farcasanu, Al. Cretzianu, C. Visoianu) (Folder 4-7)
  - Romanian National Committee, 1948-1975 (Contd.) (Box 20., Folder 1-9)
  - Romanian National Committee, 1948-1975 (Contd.) (Box 21., Folder 1-3)
  - Romanian University Institute Carol I, 1951-1962. Includes correspondence with Manuila (Folder 4-5)
  - Romanians in foreign countries, 1950-1959 (Folder 6)
  - Tito, Josip Broz, 1948 (Folder 7)
  - United States
    - Brochures concerning the status of refugees, 1951-1954 (Box 22., Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings concerning world politics, 1948 (Folder 2-3)
  - Voice of America, 1949. Samples of political analyses (Folder 4)
  - Miscellany (Folder 5)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1938-1959
  - 2 prints depicting Iuliu Maniu (Box 23., Folder 1)
  - 1 print depicting Grigore Gafencu, 1939 (Folder 2)
  - 2 prints depicting Marie, Consort of Ferdinand, King of Romania, 1865-1927, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - 2 prints depicting Al. Vaida-Voievod, N. Iorga, A. C. Cuza, A. Calinescu, and others, 1938-1939 (Folder 4)
  - 9 prints related to activities of the Assembly of Captive European Nations, 1959 (Folder 5)
  - 5 unidentified prints, 1956 (Folder 6)